<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reviews on Lucas Roesler</title>
    <link>http://lucasroesler.com/tags/reviews/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reviews on Lucas Roesler</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://lucasroesler.com/tags/reviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Living Our Culture at Teem via Peer Reviews</title>
      <link>http://lucasroesler.com/2017/04/living-our-culture-at-teem-via-peer-reviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 12:16:11 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lucasroesler.com/2017/04/living-our-culture-at-teem-via-peer-reviews/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About a year ago we set down to document the core values of the engineering at
Teem. After a lot of discussion we narrowed it to three core ideas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maximize positive impact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;communicate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be a good friend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would add one more unofficial value: mentorship and continuous learning.
About the same time we also started thinking about how we describe/define an
engineers career path and we quickly realized that measuring progress is hard
and that measuring commitment to our core values is even harder.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-these-values&#34;&gt;Why these values?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First a quick aside to breakdown what we are trying to convey in these three
ideals. Maximize positive impact, communicate, and be a good friend are simply
the short go to phrases we use to describe the overarching culture that we
believe we live and strive for. They are easy measuring sticks that we can use
in any scenario to remind ourselves who we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maximize Positive Impact&lt;/strong&gt; is our most aspirational value. It is the value you
will most likely hear an engineer repeat during a discussion and has the
largest impact on the &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; we are doing. We think that our engineers maximize
their positive impact by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having a &lt;strong&gt;focus on the user&lt;/strong&gt;. Our users are everything; without them,
there would be no Teem.  We are creating products that change how people
live and interact with their work environment and ultimately with each
other. Every engineer should strive to understand the user and the problems
that they experience in the workplace. Thanks to brilliant leadership on the
product team, every person at Teem has access to the data, research, and
recorded sessions with our users. Read the summaries and watch these
sessions. Better yet, ask to join the calls! Focus on the user and the rest
will fall into place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having a &lt;strong&gt;bias towards action&lt;/strong&gt;. If you see a problem, fix it. Have a new
idea, build a prototype. Communicate, but don&amp;rsquo;t rely on consensus
before acting. Seek others’ input, but be decisive. Ultimately, we would
rather test a hypothesis cheaply than be paralyzed by over analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;understanding that &lt;strong&gt;shipping beats perfection&lt;/strong&gt;. We want and need to
ship quickly, learning from our users and iterating. This is not an excuse
for low quality nor skipping user research. In fact, it requires both
high quality and research so that we are building the right thing from the
start and so that we can quickly build on top of our previous work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communicate&lt;/strong&gt;, this is the &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we get things done.  No person is an island,
we are team of engineers building a product together. Good communication
happens when&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you &lt;strong&gt;seek feedback often&lt;/strong&gt;. Feedback protects us from complacency. In what
and how we build products and in our careers. Career development is called
development for a reason. If you think it’s just going to happen, then
you’re doing it wrong. You build your career the same way you build the
products we deliver. Be proactive in seeking out candid feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you &lt;strong&gt;listen well&lt;/strong&gt;. Feedback only works if you &lt;em&gt;listen&lt;/em&gt;. This is not the
same as blindly following what others tell you. Hear people out, strive to
understand their position, and act accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you are &lt;strong&gt;open, very open&lt;/strong&gt;. Over communicate internally and don’t wait for
permission or for someone else to do it for you. We expect every engineer to
make an impact and to share what they are doing. Share screenshots in slack,
proactively volunteer to demo to the engineering team or even to the company
during our town halls, dive deep with a Lunch and Learn, or get others
involved with a Lunch and Destroy. Building things is only part of our job
&amp;ndash; the rest is telling people what we did and the positive impact it will
have on the team and ultimately our customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you &lt;strong&gt;voice your opinions&lt;/strong&gt;. Anyone’s allowed to argue their opinions — even
in areas other than their own. But we also listen, seek conflicting
opinions, and flex in the face of new info. Have strong opinions, but hold
them weakly. If you’re going to voice your opinion, be humble.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be a good friend.&lt;/strong&gt; There’s a theme here. We work with friends, we work for
friends, act like a good friend. Anything that’s broken is an opportunity to
make Teem better. Be the type of teammate you want to work with. Openly and
productively acknowledge weaknesses. Talk about possibilities, don’t focus on
negativity. “Don’t be a jerk” has been one of our core values from the
beginning , but it goes beyond simply avoiding &amp;ldquo;jerk-ness&amp;rdquo;, friends go out of
their way to help each other. At Teem we expect our friends to: foster
learning, focus on impact not your ego, no half-ass helping, proactively
protect your team&amp;rsquo;s time, don&amp;rsquo;t be subtly racist, sexist, homophobic,
transphobic, ageist, or foster any other kind of bias, and finally don&amp;rsquo;t take
your teammates for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that these values are not only ideas that describe
Teem, but are aspirational. Teem is made up of people, we can get distracted or
make mistakes. But these values are constant reminders and guide posts for who
we are and who we want be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;peer-reviews&#34;&gt;Peer Reviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your core values are not simply statements you make.  Sure you can make a
statement that these are the most important values to you, but ultimately your
true values are those things that you do and repeat. It is too easy to let your
values slip and change over time, especially in a quickly growing startup.
Teem was not even 30 people when I started; we just cracked 100 earlier this
year. We have attacked this culture issue in two ways.  First, you need to seed
the team with the right people, i.e. hiring. Over time we have worked on the
interview process and candidate assessment process to help us  find those
people that not only share but will reinforce our core values. But that is a
one time event, we wanted a process that would let us remember and consistently
live these values throughout the year.  With a lot of help from Dal, one of our
product managers, general bad-ass, and jack-of-all-trades, we developed a
peer review system that allows our engineering and product teams self-assess
how we are doing not only from a purely technical skill level but also in all of
the other skills that make up and reflect the core values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half of the review form directly addresses our core values. On a simple 5
points scale, we rate each other for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maximize Positive Impact&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well does this person focus on our users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they have a bias for action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well do you trust this person to deliver on their commitments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communicate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well does this person listen?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well does this person voice their opinions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How open is this person? Do you know what they&amp;rsquo;re working on?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second half of the form address technical and leadership ability. This
section has two twists.  First, we use a Fibonacci scale to rate skill levels.
We purposefully do this to recognize that technical talent and ability is not
linear. Skills are cumulative and it is often easy to learn the basics but then
much hard to gain and demonstrate high level mastery.  The second twist, we
have a little bit of fun with the scale, mostly because Dal is a huge Star Wars
fan, by labeling each level of the scale with a title from the Jedi Academy:
Padawan, Jedi, Jedi Knight, and Jedi Master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given this person&amp;rsquo;s role - what jedi level would you rate their skill?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Padawan - learning the stack, learning to be dependable, takes a little
bit longer to get sh** done but still delivers, teachable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi - owns our stack, gets sh** done, is teachable, teaches others,
thinks critically &amp;amp; questions the status quo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi Knight - bamf, great teacher, mentor to many, constantly learning,
constantly shipping or the equivalent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi Master - this person goes above and beyond Jedi Knight and you would
consider an industry leader.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you rate this person&amp;rsquo;s technical leadership?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Padawan - Ships fixes and features that require days of focus, but often
needs guidance either technically or when communicating with the rest
of the team. Most work receives direction from experienced teammates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi - can handle significant, multiple-week-long features all by
themselves.  If the patch they just submitted is causing a problem,
they’re quick to fix it, add a new unit test, and communicate exactly
what went wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi Knight - go-to person for at least one very large, well-defined
chunk of the codebase. They own more than just a feature.  They
maintain this entire section by guiding design,  training newcomers,
managing contributions, and regularly fixing bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi Master - completely and repeatedly own the design of entire
products.  They see the edge cases coming, ask great questions, and in
general are the person you want reviewing your work.  This is related
to but not always the same as their skill level in their chapter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you rate this person&amp;rsquo;s project leadership?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Padawan - Everyone starts here.  Often relies on other to define project
goals, most projects are with more experienced teammates, consistently
delivers on reasonably well-defined projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi -  proactively communicates issues as they arise, able to prioritize
tasks within multiple-week-long projects, you trusted to handle
significant multiple-week-long features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi Knight - Regularly leads small teams of developers, is comfortable
with and is able to remove ambiguity, you would trust this person to
keep large months long initiatives moving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi Master - one of the best communicators of complicated technical
subjects, tradeoffs, and decisions; they  can assemble and guide the
team needed to deliver a project,  they can be set free with a poorly
defined problem, go into a cave with their team, and show up on the
other side with a shippable solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you rate this person&amp;rsquo;s people leadership?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Padawan - This person is a good friend, listens well, and you trust their
advice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi - This person helps remove confusion, they understand how we work at
Teem, and is a good mentor to help onboard people to become
Teem-mates!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi Knight - They  help you find the right challenges to help you grow,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they can de-escalate conflicts and build consensus between team members,
and have gained your trust.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jedi Master - Not only is this person a Jedi Knight, but they provide
Yoda level leadership by actively finding and removing distractions and
defines process that helps us get more done with less stress. Sometimes
they need a piggyback ride through the jungle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we end with an open feedback section: &amp;ldquo;Any advice or kudos for this
person that will help them become or continue to be a good friend and
coworker?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every six weeks we ask the everyone in engineering and product to answer these
question for 3 &amp;ndash; 5 people via a Google Form. At the very minimum, the peer
review process let&amp;rsquo;s us remind everyone about our core values.  But we have
designed it to not simply remind, but also force them to think critically about
these values, and simply participating in the process allows them to live these
values by providing the opportunity to communicate as a friend to your peer and
even a chance to practice a little mentorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, every question has a corresponding point value that I then take and
aggregate into a report so that people can track their progress over time. This
part has long been a time consuming process, but I have recenty automated the
report generation using Python, Pandas, and Jupyter notebooks so that the
entire review process will take just about a 10 mins to generate all of the
review packets for the engineering team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have done this  just short of a year now and has been well received so far.
Perhaps the most important factor in how well this has worked is that peer
reviews are strictly used for self-improvement. While I facilitate the review
process for the team, we do not document these in some employee file somewhere
to drudge up and use against people during an annual review. These are more
like a &amp;ldquo;blameless post-mortem&amp;rdquo; for the past 6 weeks. Ultimately, and by design,
they are a tool to practice all of our core values, a chance to &amp;ldquo;communicate
like a good friend and help your teammates improve and maximize their impact in
the company and for our users.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>