<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on Lucas Roesler</title>
    <link>//lucasroesler.com/tags/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on Lucas Roesler</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="//lucasroesler.com/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Action Packed Functions</title>
      <link>//lucasroesler.com/2019/09/action-packed-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//lucasroesler.com/2019/09/action-packed-functions/</guid>
      <description>Last month, GitHub announced new improved CI/CD with GitHub Actions. Since then, I have experimented with the new Action workflows and created an Action that wraps the faas-cli so that you can easily build and deploy your functions directly from GitHub.
My initial interactions with the new GitHub Actions were not great, they really meant it when they said &amp;ldquo;public beta&amp;rdquo;. BUT!!! Having said that, there is clearly a lot of promise in GitHub Actions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing OpenFaaS KinD-ly</title>
      <link>//lucasroesler.com/2019/04/developing-openfaas-kind-ly/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//lucasroesler.com/2019/04/developing-openfaas-kind-ly/</guid>
      <description>There are several ways to run small Kubernetes clusters: k3s and k3d, minikube, and microk8s to name a few. Currently, my favorite is the Kubernetes provided by Docker Desktop for Mac. But this doesn&amp;rsquo;t help my friends (or myself) when I am on a Linux laptop. It would be nice to have one lightweight and shared environment for Kubernetes.
Luckily, one of the Kubernetes groups has released KinD - Kubernetes in Docker.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When sequential tests aren&#39;t</title>
      <link>//lucasroesler.com/2019/02/when-sequential-tests-arent/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//lucasroesler.com/2019/02/when-sequential-tests-arent/</guid>
      <description>At work we have been expanding the testing coverage of our auth service and have discovered the perfect storm of edge cases around test caching and Go&amp;rsquo;s test building. In short, we had tests that looked like they were passing locally but would fail sporadically in CI because Go will run the tests inside of a package sequentially but build and test each package in parallel (up to the number of CPU cores).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>